Guide to the Chancellor of the University of Pittsburgh, Wesley W. Posvar, Administrative Files, 1967-1991 UA.2.10.1967-1991
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Chancellor of the University of Pittsburgh, Wesley W. Posvar, Administrative Files
1967-1991
ULS Archives & Special Collections
University of Pittsburgh. Chancellor
UA.2.10.1967-1991
180.4 Linear Feet (433 boxes)
This collection comprises material pertaining to all aspects of Wesley Posvar's administration as Chancellor of the University of Pittsburgh from 1967 to 1991. Topics of interest include student unrest in the 1960s and 1970s, the growing role of medical research within the University, affirmative action and the University's interest in international studies.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Scope and Content Notes
This collection contains a large amount of material pertaining to all aspects of Wesley Posvar's administration as Chancellor of the University of Pittsburgh from 1967 to 1991. In 1984 Posvar changed his title from Chancellor to President, but the office and duties remained the same.
The majority of this collection is comprised of correspondence, but other records include reports, press releases, articles, and speeches. The first twenty-four record groups of the collection reflect each academic year that Posvar was Chancellor and these records were maintained in the order in which they were filed by the Office of the Chancellor. While extensive records were transferred to the University Archives for Academic Years 1968 through 1981 and 1991, the amount of material present for Academic Years 1982 to 1990 is limited. Folders from 1968 to 1981 also often include a scope note that lists many of the documents found in that folder.
Record Group XXV contains additional material from throughout the first twenty-four record groups. Record Group XXVI contains subject files on the Chancellor's residence, faculty unionization efforts, minority recruitment, long-range planning, speeches, and the Medical and Health Care Division of the University, among others. Record Group XXVII contains minutes and agenda from Executive and Senior Staff meetings and Record Group XXVIII contains chronological files of correspondence from 1971 to 1978 and July 1983 to July 1991.
Biography
Wesley Wentz Posvar was born in Topeka, Kansas, on September 14, 1925, and was raised in Cleveland, Ohio. He attended the United States Military Academy at West Point, where he graduated first in the class of 1946, before serving as an aircraft test pilot. Posvar won a Rhodes Scholarship, attending Oxford University where he earned Bachelor and Master of Arts degrees in philosophy, politics and economics. His first teaching position was at West Point from 1951 to 1954 before joining the long-range planning program at the Air Force headquarters in the Pentagon in Washington, D.C. In 1957 Posvar became a professor of political science at the Air Force Academy in Colorado Springs. From 1962 to 1964, he was a Littauer Fellow at Harvard's Graduate School of Public Administration, where he earned a Master of Public Administration degree and a Ph.D. in political science.
In addition to his role as a professor, Posvar was chairman of the Division of Social Sciences at the Air Force Academy when he was contacted in 1966 about the position of Chancellor at the University of Pittsburgh. On January 13, 1967, after a quick but rigorous interview process, the University's Trustees announced that Posvar would become the Chancellor of the University on June 1, 1967. Posvar was the first Chancellor to live at the Chancellor's residence on Devonshire Street, which was donated to the University by Leon Falk just prior to Posvar's selection.
Chancellor Posvar used the new state appropriated funds resulting from the University's 1966 state-related school designation to provide for the general operation of the University while private and corporate donations were used to promote programs at which Pitt would excel. With an eye toward long-range planning and control over the budget, Posvar was also able to repay the University's debt in 1976. During his time as Chancellor, the University created several new academic units, including the Honors College, University Center for International Studies, and the University Center for Social and Urban Research, to reflect Posvar's emphasis on a more diverse and accomplished campus that benefited the regional community.
Posvar focused the University on research as a means of gaining prominence. In 1973 he hired Dr. Thomas Detre to head the Western Psychiatric Institute and Clinic (WPIC), where Detre began to invest the clinic's revenue back into WPIC research. This method proved successful and Detre was tasked with implementing the model throughout the hospitals of the University's Medical and Health Care Division, becoming the University of Pittsburgh Medical Center in 1990. However, as Pitt developed into a research and medical center, faculty in the arts and sciences felt that their departments and undergraduate education were taking a backseat to these new initiatives and they took a vote of no-confidence in Posvar during the Spring of 1990. Other minor scandals, including irregularities in donations made to the Department of Athletics, disagreements about whether property taxes should be paid on the Chancellor's residence, and Posvar's retirement package, marred the last few years of his term as Chancellor. Posvar retired as Chancellor in July 1991.
In addition to his work at the University of Pittsburgh, Posvar served in leadership roles in a number of organizations, such as: the Federal Emergency Management Advisory Board, Carnegie Endowment for International Peace, World Society for Ekistics, U.S. Space Foundation, and the International Studies Association. Posvar also served as an advisor to the federal government on foreign intelligence, aviation, and national emergency telecommunications.
Posvar was married to Mildred Miller, an internationally known mezzo-soprano opera singer, and was father to a son, Wesley William, and two daughters, Marina and Lisa. In May 2000, Pitt named its largest campus classroom building, the Forbes Quadrangle, Wesley W. Posvar Hall. Posvar died on July 27, 2001, in Ligonier, Pa.
Acquisition Information
Deposited by the Office of the Chancellor in several transfers during the 1980s and 1990s.
Arrangement
Record Groups I through XXIV each represent one fiscal year of Posvar's term as Chancellor and the files within each record group were maintained in the original Chancellor's Office filing scheme, which organized documents by subject matter. The filing system for a typical year is as follows:
1.0. Academic Programs (Provost, Schools and other academic departments)
2.0 Athletics (Athletic Director, Sports teams, Pitt Band, Varsity Letter Club)
3.0 University Boards, Committees and Memberships (Board of Trustees, University Senate, Institutions where the University was a member, Organizations where the Chancellor served in a leadership role, University committees of which the Chancellor was a member)
4.0. Administration and Planning (Facilities, Finance, Planning and Budget, Personnel)
5.0. Office of the Chancellor (Activities, Events and Speeches of Chancellor Posvar)
6.0. Program Development and Public Affairs (Alumni Affairs, Public Relations, Government Relations, University News and Publications)
7.0. Student Affairs (Student Activities and Organizations, Admissions and Aid, Commencement, Homecoming, Scholarships and Awards)
8.0. Miscellaneous (Additional boards, centers and other matters, including Black Studies and the State Board of Education)
This arrangement was fairly consistent from 1969 until fiscal year 1984, when it was replaced by a new filing scheme.
Previous Citation
Chancellor of the University of Pittsburgh, Wesley W. Posvar, Administrative Files, 1967-1991, UA.2.10.1967-1991, University of Pittsburgh Archives
University of Pittsburgh; Universities and colleges -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh -- Records and correspondence; Universities and colleges -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh -- Administration; Posvar, Wesley Wentz; University of Pittsburgh. Chancellor
- Academic Year 1967/68, I.
  - Academic Programs, 1967-1968; 1.0.
    - Academic Programs, 1967-1968; 1.0.
      - Academic Programs - General (Box 1, Folder 1.0.)
    - Academic and Professional Schools and Centers, 1967-1968; 1.1.
      - Academic and Professional Schools and Centers - General, 1.1.0.
        - Membership List of the Graduate Faculty for The Academic Disciplines (Box 1, Folder 1.1)
      - College of Arts and Sciences (CAS), 1.1.1.
        - CAS - General (Box 1, Folder 1.1.1)
          Scope and Content Notes
          Academic Integrity Guidelines for the School of Liberal Arts; Pitt student, Paula Molnick, wins first place in short story category of the Atlantic Monthly; Report of "Liberal Arts Cabinet, 1966-1967"; Department of Political Science recommends "Full Graduate Faculty Status" for Dr. Posvar; Report: "Chancellor's Meeting with the staff of the School of Liberal Arts"; Report: "The School of the Liberal Arts for the Academic Year, 1966-1967"; Establishment of Faculty of Arts and Sciences with Professor David Halliday as Dean; and Memo from Dr. Halliday explaining new arrangement of FAS with Organization Chart.
        - Division of Humanities and Division of Natural Sciences (Box 1, Folder 1.1.1.1 and 1.1.1.2)
          Letter from Chairmen of Humanities expressing concern of future welfare of Humanities; Permanent appointment of the Andrew Mellon Professor of English; and Curriculum Vitae of possible candidates: Osborne B. Hardison Jr., Joseph Hillis Miller, and Albert C. Hamilton.
        - Division of Social Sciences (Box 1, Folder 1.1.1.3)
          Proposed establishment of a Bureau of Psychological Services; Dr. George Peter Murdoch, Anthropology Department, awarded Wilbur Lucius Cross Medal by Yale University; Outline and objectives of the National Institute of Mental Health Objectives of the Department of Psychology; and Comment of "Committee on Evaluation of the Department of Psychology."
      - Graduate School of Business, 1.1.2.
        - Reports and Booklets (Box 1, Folder 1.1.2)
          "Management Programs for Executives"; "The Graduate School of Business Position"; and "Management Programs for Executives" 38th and 39th sessions.
      - School of Education, 1.1.3.
        - School of Education - General (Box 1, Folder 1.1.3)
          The need to broaden graduate programs (especially math and natural sciences) for teachers in Pittsburgh Schools; Teacher education programs receive program approval from Department of Public Instruction of the Commonwealth of Pennsylvania; Letter of recognition of excellence accorded the School of Education by Kettering Foundation for educational researchers in the public schools; Proposals under Education Professions Development Act; Proposal for establishment of formal consortium of Schools/College of Education for Penn State, Temple and Pitt with draft of Constitution and By-Laws; and Consortium among Pittsburgh schools, Diocesan schools, Pitt and other institutions of higher education in this area.
      - School of Engineering, 1.1.4.
        - School of Engineering - General (Box 1, Folder 1.1.4)
          Analysis of difference between "science" and "engineering" by Dean H.E. Hoelscher; Notes on School of Engineering by Dean Hoelscher; "Pitt" release: "Pitt Engineering School Announces Curriculum Revision"; and Accreditation by ECPD of engineering programs at Pitt.
        - Weidlein Chair (Box 1, Folder 1.1.4.1)
          Establishment of Edward Ray Weidlein (Professor of Environmental Engineering) Chair, a gift from Lt. Gen. Richard K. and Mrs. Mellon to the School of Engineering.
        - Gwilym A. Price Lectures (Box 1, Folder 1.1.4.2)
      - College of General Studies (CGS), 1.1.5.
        - CGS - General (Box 1, Folder 1.1.5)
          The need for a broader educational opportunity for part-time graduate study and a Letter from Dean Viers Adams regarding better utilization of facilities for night classes.
      - School of Law and Graduate School of Library and Information Science, 1.1.6 & 1.1.7.
        - Law Degree Change and GSLIS Report (Box 1, Folder 1.1.6-1.1.7)
          The LLB degree changed to the J.D. degree, with correspondence recommending the change in law degree.
      - Graduate School of Public and International Affairs (GSPIA), 1.1.8.
        - GSPIA - General (Box 1, Folder 1.1.8)
          "Background Thoughts on Urban Affairs and Pitt"; GSPIA's Activities Focused on Improving Conditions of Negroes; GSPIA's Fall Assembly Speaker; Survey Report of the Graduate Council on Education in Public Administration; Preliminary Thoughts on International Studies at Pitt; and Urban Proposal to the Mellon Foundation.
      - Graduate School of Social Work (GSSW), 1.1.9.
        - Proposal for Undergraduate Programs in Social Work (Box 1, Folder 1.1.9)
      - Learning Research and Development Center (LRDC), 1.1.10.
        - LRDC - General (Box 1, Folder 1.1.10.)
          LRDC Board of Visitors Meeting, December 8-9, 1967; "LRDC at University of Pittsburgh" booklet; and Proposal for an Educational Research Faculty submitted by LRDC, March, 1968.
      - Space Research and Coordination Center (SRCC), 1.1.12.
        - SRCC - General (Box 2, Folder 1.1.12)
          "Arms Control & Strategic Weapons Utilities"; Copy of "Memorandum of Understanding between University of Pittsburgh and National Aeronautics and Space Administration"; Telegram advising Pitt of NASA Research Grant; Dean H. E. Hoelscher named Director of Space Research Coordination Center at Pitt, replacing Dean David Halllday; Facilities Grant NsG (F) -13; and Report and a Proposal for a Supplement to NASA Grant – NsG-416, August 1, 1967 to July 31, 1970.
      - Graduate Center for Public Works, Knowledge Availability Systems Center, and Social Science Information Center, 1.1.13, 1.1.14 & 1.1.15.
        - GCPW, KASC and SSIC Correspondence (Box 2, Folder 1.1.13-1.1.15)
      - University Science Center and Faculty of Arts and Sciences, 1.1.16 & 1.1.17.
        - Reports and Proposal (Box 2, Folder 1.1.16-1.1.17)
          A proposal to establish a Research Park, the Pittsburgh Science Center; correspondence; and USC Report to the Board of Directors, April 19, 1968.
    - Health Professions, 1967-1968; 1.2.
      - Report of Study Concerning Allied Health Professions, September 1967 (Box 2, Folder 1.2)
      - School of Dentistry, School of Medicine and College of Pharmacy (Box 2, Folder 1.2.1-1.2.4)
        Salk Hall of the Health Professions for Dentistry and Pharmacy, Dedication Book, 1967
      - Graduate School of Public Health (Box 2, Folder 1.2.5)
        Correspondence regarding funds for University-wide Center for Comprehensive Health Planning. Correspondence and Curriculum Vita of Richard A. Prindle, M.D. as prospective Dean, GSPH.
      - Health Law Center (Box 2, Folder 1.2.6)
        Letter regarding Sale of Pennsylvania Statute Tapes; Memo: "The Health Law Center and the Aspen Corporation"; Letter regarding proposed sale of assets to the Aspen Corp.; and Report on "Air Force Project LITE".
      - Comprehensive Health Planning (Box 2, Folder 1.2.7)
        Letters to begin planning for development of Academic Training, Studies and Demonstrations in Comprehensive Health Planning. "Hospitals and Comprehensive Health Planning Report."
    - International Programs, 1967-1968; 1.3.
      - International Programs - General (Box 2, Folder 1.3)
        "Proposed Structure of the International Dimension in the New Organization" Progress Report; "University of Pittsburgh International Dimensions" Booklet; Correspondence on International Programs for Central University, Quito, Ecuador, Guatemala and Nigeria; Liberian President William V.S. Tubman Visit; Annual Report to the Ford Foundation on International Activities at Pitt; and Summary of International Activities in the Professional Schools.
    - Graduate Programs, 1967-1968; 1.4.
      - "An Assessment of Quality in Graduate Education" by A. M. Carter (Box 2, Folder 1.4)
    - Grading Systems and American Council on Education's Academic Internship Program, 1967-1968; 1.5 & 1.6.
      - Change in Grading System and ACE Internship (Box 2, Folder 1.5-1.6)
    - Urban Programs, 1967-1968; 1.7.
      - Urban Programs - General (Box 3, Folder 1.7)
        "The University's Urban Programs" report to the Chancellor, November 1967; University Programs for the Culturally Disadvantaged — Interim Report (University-Community Educational Programs); "The Pittsburgh Survey: A Social Science Research Program and Proposal"; Statement from Dr. Posvar to Pitt students regarding race relations within the University; Negro Educational Emergency Drive (NEED) Urban Programs; "Ghetto Projects"; Establishment of the Martin Luther King, Jr., Scholarship and Fellowship Fund; Proposal to the University of Pittsburgh in the Current Racial Crisis; "Urban Government for Urban America"; Milton Eisenhower letter; and "A Plan for Social Justice Programs with Selected Examples."
    - National Science Foundation - Science Development Program (NSF-SDP) Site Visit, 1967-1968; 1.8.
      - Correspondence Regarding Site Visit (Box 3, Folder 1.8)
    - Cooperative PhD Program with Pittsburgh Theological Seminary, 1967-1968; 1.9.
      - Correspondence Regarding Cooperative PhD Program (Box 3, Folder 1.9)
    - Continuing Education for Women and Pitt-Hong Kong University Cooperative Agreement, 1967-1968; 1.10 & 1.11.
      - Caryl Kline Position in University and Clippings on Visit of Vice Chancellor of Chinese University of Hong Kong (Box 3, Folder 1.10-1.11)
    - Republicans Speak on Vital Problems (RSVP) Program, Department of Defense Project Themis, and Proposed Graduate School of Arts and Sciences, 1967-1968; 1.13, 1.14 & 1.15.
      - Correspondence and Reports (Box 3, Folder 1.13-1.15)
    - Regional Campuses, 1967-1968; 1.16.
      - Regional Campuses - General (Box 3, Folder 1.16)
        "Policy Guidance" for Regional Campuses and a statement of University of Pittsburgh on The Heald-Hobson Report.
      - Bradford, Greensburg, Johnstown and Titusville Campuses (Box 3, Folder 1.16.1-1.16.4)
    - International Programs, 1967-1968; 1.17.
      - International Programs Reports (Box 3, Folder 1.17)
        Gardner Report, "AID and the Universities"; "Pitt Ecuador Project Ending" article; Annual report to Ford Foundation on International Activities of University of Pittsburgh; Establishment of the University Center for International Studies; Report of Chancellor's Committee on Reorganization of the International Dimension of the University of Pittsburgh; and "End of Contract Report - University of Pittsburgh, June 30, 1968" with Central University, Quito, Ecuador.
    - Message to Students, 1967-1968; 1.18.
      - Message to Students on the New Urban and Black Studies Programs and Policies (Box 3, Folder 1.18)
    - Pittsburgh Conference on Urban Organization, November 15, 1967; 1.19.
      - Pittsburgh Conference on Urban Organization (Box 3, Folder 1.19)
  - Administrative Management, 1967-1968; 2.0.
    - Policy Manuals, 1967-1968; 2.1.
      - Policies Regarding Drugs, Computer Use, Discrimination and the Use of Private Social Clubs for University Functions (Box 4, Folder 2.1)
    - Planning and Administrative Information, 1967-1968; 2.2.
      - Problems of University Planning, Organization and Administration (Box 4, Folder 2.2)
      - Management Information System (Box 4, Folder 2.2.1)
      - Program-Budget Systems and Long-Range Planning and Analysis (Box 4, Folder 2.2.2-2.2.3)
        Plans to develop a planning-programming-budgeting system covering the academic area.
      - Intra-University Communications (Box 4, Folder 2.2.4)
        "Improving Intra-University Communications". Annual Report to the Kellogg Foundation by the Interuniversity Communications Council (EDUCOM).
      - INTRACOM (Box 4, Folder 2.2.5)
        Formation of a group of key members of the University staff who are most knowledgeable in the communications sciences and would thus be known as "intracom".
      - Comprehensive Facilities Planning Program (Box 4, Folder 2.2.6)
        "Commonwealth of Pennsylvania - Higher Education Facilities - Comprehensive Planning (1967)". Confirmation of approval of grant for comprehensive facilities planning program.
    - Organization and Functions, 1967-1968; 2.3.
      - Organization and Functions - General, 2.3.
        - Reorganization Proposals (Box 4, Folder 2.3)
          New Divisional arrangement of FAS; Reorganization letter from Dr. Posvar to Faculty and Staff, September 15, 1967. Proposed organization chart, July 17, 1967; and "The Organization of the University of Pittsburgh" Report by Heald, Hobson and Associates, July 17, 1967.
      - Organization of the University and Office of the Chancellor, 2.3.1 & 2.3.2.
        - Organization Charts for the University and Office of the Chancellor (Box 4, Folder 2.3.1-2.3.2)
        - Executive Assistant to the Chancellor and Secretary of the University (Box 4, Folder 2.3.2.1-2.3.2.2)
        - Director of Athletics (Box 4, Folder 2.3.2.3)
          NCAA By-Laws, Article 6, Section 2, relative to use of funds for the recruitment and entertainment of prospective athletes.
        - Assistant to the Chancellor (Box 4, Folder 2.3.2.4)
          Areas of responsibility for Helen P. Rush; Brochure on Heinz Chapel; and "Experimental Secretarial Program" report.
      - Provost of the University, 2.3.3.
        - Provost of the University - General (Box 4, Folder 2.3.3)
          Charles H. Peake appointed Provost; Final Committee Report and Recommendation of Provost Search Committee, May 10, 1968 (returned to Chancellor's office per their request 11/12/80); Organization Chart for Provost Office; Copy of Draft Prospectus, "The Experimental College" from S. Gow to Peake, February 23, 1968.
        - College of Arts and Sciences (CAS) and CAS Division of the Humanities (Box 4, Folder 2.3.3.1-2.3.3.1a)
          Establishment of a Faculty of Arts and Sciences with Prof. David Halliday as Dean; FAS Organization Chart; and Duties of Dr. Putnam F. Jones.
        - Graduate School of Business (Box 4, Folder 2.3.3.2)
          Memo': "Undergraduate Business Education"; "Proposed Objectives for a Graduate School of Business Administration" adopted by faculty, 1958; "An Open letter to the applicants for the Master of Business Administration Program at Pitt's Graduate School of Business"; "Advantages of a 3-term (11 month) Program for the Graduate School of Business"; and Report of Viewers.
        - School of Education (Box 4, Folder 2.3.3.3)
          "The Preparation of Educational Leaders," Fall, 1967. Policy statement for student teachers in case of strikes or other work stoppage, February 1968.
        - School of Engineering (Box 4, Folder 2.3.3.4)
          Proposed change of name from School of Engineering to College of Engineering; "The 5-Year Growth Policy for Engineering," January 18, 1968; Correspondence regarding alleged bribery solicitation; Construction of a new School of Engineering; and Statement on present Mining Engineering Degree option and why a change is necessary.
        - School of General Studies (Box 4, Folder 2.3.3.5)
          Ways and means to increase enrollment in the School of General Studies.
        - School of Law (Box 4, Folder 2.3.3.6)
          Draft of "Responsibility for the Health Law Center and Related Activities," August 9, 1967
        - Graduate School of Library and Information Sciences (Box 4, Folder 2.3.3.7)
          Statistics of member libraries of Pittsburgh Regional Library Center. Grant from Office of HEW to begin preparations to conduct an Institute for Training in Librarianship.